"Previously on The Mentalist..."
"She told me Red John has a tattoo
on his left shoulder"
"three dots."
That's my leverage.
Gather all five suspects together
at the same place, same time
and then start checking
for the tattoo.
How do we do that?
- Meet me at 8:00 on Thursday night.
- Fine.
Thursday night at 8:00.
- I'll need your help.
- Well, then you've got it.
If you don't show up,
he will assume you're Red John.
If I do this, will you and Jane drop
the whole that "I'm Red John" business?
For once and for all.
- You really think you've got him?
- I do.
- I want to be there when you end this.
- I was hoping you'd say that.
Red John.
Nothing would give me more pleasure
than to be with you there tonight.
Red John... has a tattoo.
Three dots on his left arm.
On his shoulder. And you all...
are gonna show me...
now.
Let's go. Come on.
That's it. Take it off.
Nonsense.
Very good.
It's not what you think.
You got it wrong.
I'm not Red John.
Patrick, wait. Patrick!
Look... here.
Look.
On your feet.
Over with those two.
You stay there.
Okay, you three...
Over against that wall...
now.
"Wait! No!"
Call the fire department
and E.M.T.s
let them know that there's
multiple casualties
- and set up a perimeter.
- Yes, ma'am.
- Give me your flashlight. I'm going in.
- Here you go.
Jane.
Agent Smith.
Agent Smith, it's Teresa Lisbon.
Are you okay?
- What happened?
- There was an explosion.
The E.M.T.s are on their way.
They're gonna help you.
- Don't move!
- What?
Put your hands in the air,
or I'll shoot! Do it!
Okay, listen, I don't know
what you're talking about.
You're clearly
making a big mistake.
Which way did Smith go?
- Oh, my God, Lisbon.
- Boss!
We have to find Smith.
He's Red John.
I'll get help.
Jane?
Can you hear me?
Jane? Come on.
- You okay?
- I'm fine.
The doctors say Jane's stable.
There's no major trauma or anything.
He's just not awake.
They found the remains
of three people.
Positive I.D.s for Bret Stiles, Ray Haffner
and Thomas McAllister.
Are you sure? I would think Bret Stiles
would survive a nuclear attack.
The bodies are all burnt to a crisp
but the crime techs
did spot D.N.A. tests.
Coroner's office checked it
against medical records.
Stiles, Haffner, and McAllister
are all positively dead.
Uh, what about Smith?
Any sightings?
Not yet. Rigsby and Van Pelt
are on it.
Sir?
- Ah, thought I might find you here.
- Are you all right?
Uh, I'm fine. I could use
a cup of coffee, actually.
Would you go and get me one?
We're just about to coordinate
the manhunt for Smith.
Well, you should just
go and get him.
Well, I'd like
to stay here, sir.
- Well, are...
- Cho and the team... they can handle it.
- Are you refusing a direct order?
- Well, no.
No, I just want to stay here with him.
Why don't you listen
a little more closely?
I am ordering you
to get out there
put your team together,
and get Smith.
Jane? Jane?
Where's the damn call button?
I'll...I'll get the nurse.
Jane.
Hey.
Hey boss.
Our working theory is that Red John
brought in the bomb
to kill Jane and the other suspects.
Okay, but how?
Chances are, Red John
snuck the bomb in on his person.
Crime techs have pulled
fragments of the bomb casings
from the walls...
very small fragments.
This tells us that the explosive
was dense, high-powered.
That doesn't sound homemade.
No. Military grade's my bet
which means it could be traceable.
These are the most likely sources.
I want you to check for any recent thefts
- or missing explosives from any of them.
- All right, will do.
- Got something?
- Yeah.
Lisbon wounded Smith
before he escaped.
He's walking around
with a bullet.
Oh. Well, hospitals have
to declare gunshot wounds
so he can't go to an E.R.
Right, so he needs a doctor
who'll keep quiet.
Smith's based
here in Sacramento
so I looked into some of his
old cases around town.
He was part of a task force
that arrested
Dr. Alek Lavrov last year
in south Sac.
A Dr. Feelgood writing
illegal oxycontin scripts.
- So?
- So the case went bad
evidence was lost,
and Lavrov walked.
So Smith knows exactly
where to find a doctor
who won't talk to the cops.
Great, let's go check it out.
- It's not what you think.
- No?
I'm not Red John.
Patrick, wait. Look.
Welcome back.
Lisbon.
There was an explosion
at your house.
- How long have I been out?
- 12 hours.
Reede Smith is Red John.
I saw the tattoo on his shoulder.
He's not the only one.
McAllister has one, too.
He's dead.
So are Stiles and Haffner.
- And Bertram.
- Bertram?
- He has the tattoo as well.
- Oh, my God.
He was just here.
He was standing over you.
He...he was trying
to get me to leave.
He was gonna kill you.
- Where are my clothes?
- Slow down, okay?
- Just...
- No, it's okay. We don't have time.
- Jane. Jane.
- Where are my clothes?
This is Teresa Lisbon.
Put out a statewide alert
for the apprehension
of Reede Smith
and Gail Bertram.
Yes, Director Bertram.
Approach with caution.
They're considered
armed and dangerous.
One of them is Red John.
Oh my God!
Move along, ma'am.
Police business.
God!
Yes.
- The bullet is still inside you.
- No crap! Get it out!
This is going to hurt.
Are you sure you won't
take something for the pain?
No... No. I gotta stay sharp.
As you like.
God!
Tiger, tiger.
Smith in there?
Yeah. He's screaming
his head off.
He won't be a problem.
How you wanna do it?
I just got word
from inside CBI.
Couple of agents are coming here
right now looking for Smith.
- So what do we do?
- We hurry.
You go get him.
I'll run interference if CBI shows.
You got it.
Hey. Take him out the back.
Do it there.
- He made me do this. I'm innocent.
- Shut up.
I would have called the police
as soon as he left.
- I don't want any trouble!
- Quiet!
You association?
Tiger, tiger.
Why didn't you call us?
Funnily enough,
I got trust issues.
Hey, you gotta trust
your friends.
I'm here to help you.
Can you walk?
I need to sew him up.
He'll bleed.
I can walk.
- Detective Cordero, right?
- Agent Rigsby.
How are ya?
He's, Sac P.D.
worked the Kirkland shooting.
- This is Agent Grace Van Pelt.
- Hi.
What brings you
to south Sac?
- We're chasing up a lead on Reede...
- Reede Smith.
AKA Red John. Looks like we beat you
to the punch.
One of my guys is in there
getting him right now.
You want us to cover
the back?
- No. No, we got it.
- You sure?
Hey, we might not be CBI,
but we know what we're doing.
Okay. Excuse me.
Yep?
Rigsby, where are you?
Outside the doctor's office.
Looks like Smith's inside.
Are there policemen with you?
Yeah. Why?
Okay, listen carefully.
Do not trust anyone
in law enforcement.
Anyone at all.
Do you understand?
You got it. Thanks.
Let's, go take a look
around back.
Wait a minute. Hey!
Where are you going?
Car's back this way.
Everything's taken care of.
We got a safe house nearby,
fresh clothes, a doctor...
A trip out of town.
A safe house, huh?
You know, I said that
to someone once.
Yeah? What happened after that?
I shot him six times
in the back.
Come on.
Damn it.
Drop your weapon!
Stop!
- You all right?
- Yeah! You good?
Yeah.
Smith got away during the fight.
So did the detective.
Boss, they were trying
to kill Smith and us. Why?
- I don't know.
- Check the shoulder.
What?
Ask him to check
the left shoulder.
Have Rigsby take his shirt off
and look at his shoulder.
Lisbon wants you to check
his left shoulder.
What the hell?
He's got it.
He's got the tattoo.
Boss, what's happening?
All right, bring him in
and don't let anybody else get to him.
Bring him in.
What do we know about the cop
who attacked you?
This is the one we caught.
Officer Paul Wiehagen.
Six years on the force.
Exemplary record
a couple of commendations,
no real discipline problems.
What about the other one...
Detective Cordero?
Put a call in to his captain.
Said he called in sick an hour ago.
And still no sign of Bertram.
Let's focus on the one we do have.
Maybe Jane will figure it out.
Did someone send you
to kill Reede Smith?
I got nothing to say.
Why were you gonna
murder him?
What about the tattoo?
What's it mean?
You're not a big talker.
I get it.
Loose lips sink ships
and all that.
The bad news is,
you have a lousy poker face.
So we're gonna play a little
game of show-and-tell.
I'm gonna tell you something, and you're
gonna show me with your face
whether I'm right or not.
That sound fun?
You ever steal anything?
Did you ever cheat
on your girlfriend?
Hit her?
Do you like causing pain?
I never hit a woman
in my life.
Do you belong to a secret
organization of cops
and other government officials?
Yes.
You've committed crimes
on behalf of that organization before.
Right?
Agent Smith is a member also...
The organization sent you
to the doctor's office
to kill him... right?
CBI director Gail Bertram
is also a member.
You don't know.
Too low on the totem pole, huh?
Agent Reede Smith
is Red John.
Don't know.
Gail Bertram's Red John.
That tattoo on your shoulder
is the membership sign.
I don't know
what you're talking about.
Right again.
There's a password, too...
something you say
as a greeting or a...
Distress signal.
"Tiger, tiger".
Get out of my head.
- A secret society of dirty cops.
- And Red John's a member.
Partridge.
He said "tiger, tiger" to me
right before he died.
Yes. Yes.
He was asking for help
in the hopes
that you were a member.
But if he had a tattoo
it would have been
in the autopsy report.
Well, you can't trust a file.
We have to see it.
I'll have Cho track down the body.
But Partridge could be
buried by now.
Well, have Cho bring
a shovel.
The team's looking for Smith,
Bertram's on the run.
So who's Red John?
Is it Bertram or Smith?
I need to look them
both in the eye.
Yeah, the coroner released his body,
like, two days ago.
- Murder victim, huh?
- Yeah.
I figured. That's why
we held him for so long.
Good thing you got here today.
Tomorrow there won't be
much left of him to look at.
Here we go.
Brett Partridge.
Give me a hand, huh?
He's all yours.
Give me your knife.
They dress 'em
before we burn 'em.
Don't ask me why.
Cho sent a picture.
What does it mean?
What do you think it means?
What happened with Smith?
We almost got him at his doctor's office.
That CBI team showed up.
Smith's in the wind.
That's a good place to be.
I've got some business in here
so wait for me.
Thank you, Mr. Thomas.
- We haven't seen you for a while.
- Yeah. It's nice to see you.
Smith could be anywhere by now.
I tried to trace the G.P.S.
signal on his cell phone.
It's been dead for hours.
A dirty F.B.I. agent like him
has to have a burner.
Dr. Lavrov says he didn't
get the chance to sew Smith up.
He's still walking around
with a bullet wound.
So he's in a bad way
wherever he is.
He'll get picked up
by someone eventually.
Yeah, but any cop
who finds him...
This is scary.
We can't trust anyone.
Nope.
- Agent Van Pelt.
- You gotta help me.
Agent Smith.
They're gonna kill me.
I wanna surrender.
Where are you?
Downtown.
Call Cho. He should be close.
Okay, we're on our way.
Good. Thank you.
Smith reached out to CBI.
He used the burner
the association gave him.
We were listening.
- He's turning himself in.
- Yeah. Rat.
That CBI team is on its way
to get him now.
Well, we can't have that.
Where is he?
He's in an alley not too far from here.
Our good luck.
Does he know who you are?
Nah, he didn't see me
at the doctor's office.
All right. You are now
a CBI agent.
You want to come along?
Could be fun.
No. I have some other business
to take care of.
- We'll meet up later.
- You got it.
Can you get it right
this time?
Yes sir.
Agent Reede Smith?
You out there?
Agent Van Pelt sent me.
Who are you?
Agent Oscar Cordero, CBI.
I'm here to take you in.
You gotta keep me safe.
They're everywhere.
Yeah.
We are.
God...
Back of the car now.
You didn't really think you
could get away from us, did you?
You're a big boy.
Do me a favor
and get in the trunk
yourself.
Just give me a second,
will you?
You'll have a second
in the trunk.
Now don't make me do
painful things to you.
Get in the car!
I'm gonna need a deal.
Full immunity.
I'm not saying a word
unless I can walk.
So walk.
What?
Get up off your ass
and walk.
But, hey, good luck
getting out of the building
before your friends
catch up with you.
If you tell us
everything we need to know
I promise we will put you
in a federal prison
far away from California.
Someplace
that you'll be safe.
Five years ago,
I hurt my back.
I was helping my cousin
move a stupid couch.
Doctor gave me
some pain pills.
Turns out I liked them.
I got hooked before I even knew
what was happening.
- So?
- So...
I'm chasing a gangbanger
down an alley
in Carson Springs,
and I'm out of it.
I mean, way out of it.
I thought...I thought
I was being followed.
I shot a little girl.
A 12-year-old girl.
Local cops took my blood.
They had witnesses.
They had me cold.
And then this detective
he reaches out to me
and he says
they can make it all
go away.
And they did.
The blood tests,
the witnesses...all of it?
Hell, when they
got done fixing it
the F.B.I. gave me a medal.
And exactly who are "they"?
We call ourselves
the Blake Association.
Why?
"Tiger, tiger."
"Tyger, tyger burning bright"
from the poem by Blake.
Someone's a big fan of his,
I guess.
Well, who else
is in the association?
Cops, judges, F.B.I. agents.
Anyone in law enforcement
that needs a secret covered up.
Like your drug habit.
You need a favor,
you ask for it.
You get asked to do something,
you do it.
"Tiger, tiger."
Yep.
Well, is there somebody
who's in charge?
Must be.
But I don't know who.
I just know my little group.
That's it.
But I'm guessing
there must be hundreds of us,
maybe thousands.
And nobody knows about it?
Bob Kirkland knew about it,
didn't he?
Go ahead, just say it.
Unburden yourself.
Yeah.
He knew too much.
So I killed him.
Do you know that Red John's a member
of the Blake Association?
Are you sure?
Red John had a follower.
Rebecca Anderson.
"Killed some of your guys
about four years ago."
"Yeah, Sam Bosco
and his team."
"Them."
"Someone asked me to get
F.B.I. credentials"
"so that they could access CBI."
Red John or someone
who worked for him
snuck into the CBI
and poisoned Rebecca.
"And you helped them?"
I mean, that's when I knew.
I'd...I'd done a favor
for a serial killer.
Who asked you to get
the credentials?
I don't know.
It was a phone call.
That's the way
the association works.
You never know.
You...
You're gonna be able
to keep me safe, right?
That depends.
Did you murder
my wife and daughter?
I did not murder
your wife and daughter.
I swear on my mother.
Do you believe him?
He confessed to murder.
Red John would never break
like that, not even as an act.
- Well, if Smith isn't Red John...
- That means we have work to do.
And we need help.
Who took over from Brenda Shettrick?
In media relations? Why?
Thank you for coming
on such short notice.
We have CBI consultant
Patrick Jane here
who is here to report a development
in the Red John case.
Thank you.
Ten years ago
the serial killer known as Red John
killed my wife and daughter.
Uh, we've been hunting him
diligently ever since.
Today we're pleased
to announce
that we...we finally have
a name, a face.
The director of the division
of law enforcement
Gail Bertram, is Red John.
He's armed and dangerous.
If you see him,
do not approach him.
Call the California
Bureau of Investigation at once.
Thank you.
One question at a time.
Excuse me ma'am.
So are we gonna talk
about this?
Talk about what?
Bertram is Red John.
Looks like.
And if Jane finds him,
he's gonna kill him.
Yeah.
And we're good with that?
Killing the boss?
- I am.
- Yeah.
Okay.
Just as long as we're
on the same page.
It's just weird, is all.
Does Bertram smoke?
No, I don't think so.
People get them
as gifts sometimes.
Van Pelt.
A flash drive.
Let's take a look.
There's only one file on the drive.
It's password-protected.
I'll have to brute-force it.
Cool. I've been wanting to use
my new F.P.G.A.
- Your what?
- Trust me, don't ask.
And...
We're in.
Crap.
It looks like a list.
Names, maybe?
Can you decode it?
I can try a few things...
but decoding is Jane's
department.
I'll send it to him.
Here you go.
This one isn't messing around.
Lots of peat.
Yeah, that's pretty good.
Can you put some rocks in it?
Are you sure?
This is some fine scotch.
Yeah, I'm sure.
That guy looks like you.
I need a ride.
We're on route
to the bar now.
Highway patrol
shut down the freeways
so if he runs, we've got him,
but what if he hides?
Bertram killed the bartender
in Citrus Heights.
He's got an aunt
with a house there.
You think that's
where he is?
She moved into a retirement home
about six months ago
so her place is empty now.
Sounds like a good place to hide.
What's the address?
1408 Rosemary Street.
We're on our way.
Get Cho and R.R.T. there now
and let the choppers know.
- Is he here?
- If he is. He's in there.
I got Karl and a few guys in the back.
He's not going anywhere.
Do we trust them?
I asked to see their shoulders
no tattoos.
What are you doing here?
I didn't call Sac P.D. S.W.A.T.
Well, someone asked for us.
Let's set up a command center
right here!
Listen, everybody,
I'm in charge!
Different order and district
that's way across town.
What the hell is going on?
He did it.
He called them in.
Well, why would Bertram call
S.W.A.T. to his own location?
He didn't call in one S.W.A.T. team.
He called all of them in.
This is a madhouse.
There's a whole 'nother unit
setting up out back.
We've lost control
of the scene, boss.
He's one of them.
Bertram is one of them.
We gotta shut it down.
Nobody leaves!
No one leaves!
You're clear.
Yeah...
I need something to eat.
How about Chinese?
I know a great place.
Yeah, sounds good.
They found Bertram's clothes
inside the house.
Looks like someone planted
a S.W.A.T. team outfit
in the house
before he got there.
And then called every S.W.A.T.
and R.R.T. in the area.
Any leads about who made
all those calls?
Somebody who could pull
a lot of strings at once.
Blake Association.
Boss.
May I have your attention, please?
Put down your phones
and step away from your desks.
Now.
I'm Special Agent in charge
Teresa Lisbon.
Who the hell are you?
F.B.I. supervisory
Agent Dennis Abbott.
Now I repeat, stand up
and stand away
from your desks...
Please.
We're in the middle of a manhunt
for a dangerous fugitive.
Now if you would like
to assist...
The head of this alleged
law enforcement organization
is a murderer
and a member of a massive
criminal conspiracy.
Which included F.B.I. agents.
Yes, and that's why the bureau
sent me here
from the Austin, Texas, office.
To clean up the mess.
I am holding in my hand
a writ from a federal judge.
The F.B.I.'s closing down
your organization right now.
All of you
are relieved from your active duties
as of this moment.
You can't do that.
I'm here to collect evidence.
Don't get in my way.
Let's go to work, fellas.
"Alright, alright take it easy man"
Whoa, whoa, whoa, whoa.
What's going on here?
That's yours.
Dennis Abbott, F.B.I.
you must be Patrick Jane.
They've shut us down.
We're gonna need to interview you
at some point but it can wait.
We're gonna be here for some time.
Just don't leave town.
- We have a killer to catch.
- Oh, well, that's our problem now.
You had your chance to catch him
and you blew it...
if you were really trying.
That was my favorite cup.
Yeah.
Okay, well, you see
in the funny pages.
What now?
I don't know.
Van Pelt found some coded files
in Bertram's flash drive.
Should we get started
on those?
No, it's a waste of time.
We're done.
There's nothing more
to do here.
Just go home, get some rest.
You're not quitting.
I don't believe it.
No, I'm not quitting.
I'm letting go.
It's out of our hands
for now.
But I'll be in touch.
Okay?
I'm sorry. For everything.